Guide to the Japanese-American Relocation Centers records, 1935-1953.
Japanese-American Relocation Centers records,
- Series I. Poston
  - City management
    - Block Manager's Logs- Block #326 Sept. 1942-June 1943 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Block Manager's Logs- Block #327 Sept. 1942-July 1943 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Block Manager's Logs- Block #328 Sept. 1942-June 1943 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Block Manager's Logs- Block #329 Sept. 1942-July 1943 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Block Manager's Logs- Block #330 Sept. 1942-July 1943 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Local Administration- general organization information, charts, notes and interviews about administrative organization. (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Administrative Orders #1-26, May 19, 1942-July 26, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Administrative Circulars #2-18, May 17, 1942-July 12, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Administrative Momorandums (to staff) June 6, 1942-Oct. 25, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Administrative memorandums to all camp employees, May 28, 1942-Aug. 25, 1943. (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Administrative policies Dec. 28, 1942-Feb. 6, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Administrative policies (continued) Feb. 9, 1943-Mar. 19, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Administrative policies (continued) Mar. 19-June 30, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Administrative Fiscal problems-- pay scale, notes (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Staff Forum Meetings- minutes Dec. 3, 1942-Jan. 20, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Analyses of Staff meetings, notes and report (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Staff meeting minutes July 21-Oct. 28, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Staff meeting minutes Nov. 2-11, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Block meeting lists (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Staff meeting minutes and analyses, memos, notes Nov. 16-Dec. 1, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Staff meeting minutes Dec. 2-17, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Staff meeting minutes Dec. 21-31, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Staff meeting minutes Jan. 4-Feb. 2, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Staff meeting minutes Mar. 6-June 29, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Judicial Commission- code of offenses, cases, ordinances, court dockets, Mar. 5, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Legal Division- Law and Order, weekly reports from project attorney to WRA and regional attorney June 1942-Aug. 14, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Legal Division- general information, interviews, logs, personnel, news July 1942-Aug. 1943 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Fire Department- organization, reports, problems, history Aug. 1942-June 1943 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Police Department- organization, history, notes, reports, cases, court dockets. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Post Office- organization, problems (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Transportation- 1943 report (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Trust Fund (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Land planning Board- minutes of meetings Dec. 1942-June 1943 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Community government
    - Administrative reports, report on history of self-government in Poston, report on a developing community, consultant report after one month. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Notes on community government. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Drafts of reports (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Post-strike political structure, chronology and politics Observations on council's main concerns, charts of TCC and IAB, flow charts of relationships between councils, "clique" charts, Poston Anthology (poetry) (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Central Executive Board- reports on history resignations (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Issei Advisory Board- mass resignation incident, meetings Nov. 6, 1942-May 29, 1943, regulations, member lists, proposed constitutions and amendments, Issei informal Rep. Council meeting, minutes Aug. 1942. (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Labor relations board- minutes of labor committee meting (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Merit rating board- attitudes and opinions of members on their work, description of political structure, report from committee and suggestions, member lists. (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - City Planning Board- meeting minutes June-Nov. 1942, draft of constitution. (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Pre-temporary Council II- meeting minutes July-Aug. 1942 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Temporary Community Council I- minutes and meetings May-Sept. 1942. (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Temporary Community Council I- minutes and meetings Oct. 1942-Jan. 1943 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Temporary Community Council I- minutes and meetings Feb.-May 1943 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Temporary Community Council I- data other than meeting minutes (election info., WRA manuals, memos, administrative memos, notices and instructions) (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Temporary Community Council II- meeting minutes Aug.-Nov. 1942 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Trmporary Community Council III- meeting minutes Sept.-Nov. 1942. (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Temporary Community Council III- minutes- Dec. 1942-Jan. 1943 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Temporary Community Council III-minutes Feb.-Mar. 1943, letter to FDR, letter and interview with Myers. (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Temporary Community Council III-minutes Apr.-June 1943 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Local Council I and II- meeting minutes May-July 1943 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Council Unit I- notes, letters, memos, interview, meetings, press bulletins pertaining to eventual self-gov't. (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Permanent Self-government: overall council-meeting of organizing committee for self-gov't., constituency convention, excerpts from assorted conventions, meeting minutes June 1943. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Poston Community Council: Temporary Community Council resumes preliminary reports with developing community gov't., Charter of Poston, Penal code, traffic regulations. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Poston Community Council: meeting minutes June-Sept., 1943. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Poston Community Council III- meeting minutes, interviews, observations, May 1943-June 1943 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Poston Unit administration by evacuees: evacuee interviews, opinions. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Block studies
    - Block #2- statistics, council notes, meeting minutes, study, summary (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Block #3- statistics, personality profile, block council (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Block #4, statistics, study (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Block studies- Block #5 Oct. 1942-Jan. 1943, statistics, surveys, notes on events, problems, activities, personality profile, summary (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Block #5 Mar.-Aug. 1943 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Block #6 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Block #11-statistics, sentiment, studies, Jan.-Oct. 1943 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Block #12-statistics/general summary, sentiment studies, interviews, notes on incidents, activities 1942. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Block #13-statistics, interviews, summary (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Block #14- statistics and charts, interpretation, notes on problems, profile, interview May 31, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Block #15- statistics, profile, summary (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Block #16- statistics, block profile, interview, summary (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Block #17- statistics, block study, diary, summary (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Block #18- statistics, interview, block profile, family studies, summary (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Block #19- Statistics, block profile summary, block log, July-Aug. (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Block #21- statistics, general summary, block study, diary (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Block #22- statistics, study, summary, notes (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Block #26- statistics, study, summary, interviews, notes (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Block #27- statistics, interviews, notes, diaries, block study, summary (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Block #28- few statistics, study, notes, summary (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Block # 30-statistics and charts, interviews, notes family study, notes from block meeting, diaries, notes on activities, summary (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Block #31- charts, activities notes, interview and study, summary (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Block #32- charts and statistics, block profile study, notes, interview, summary (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Block #35- statistics, Block study, notes and log, block meetings notes, personality block study (with charts, interviews, impressions and notes), "Block study method and techniques and outline." (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Block #35 (continued) personal journal and observations Jan. 4-June 24, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Block #36- notes, statistics, personality study, summary (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Block #37- statistics, summary, personality study, summary (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Block #38- summary report, statistics, personality profile. (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Block #39- interviews, statistics, summary (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Block #42- statistics and notes, personality profile, summary (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Block #43- statistics, interviews, summary report (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Block #44- statistics, interview, summary (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Block #45- notes, statistics, journal, "Girls" study, summary (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Block #46- statistics, summary, interviews (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Block #53- statistics, personality profile, notes on: background, religion, block managers, history, dining/kitchen, block meetings, strike, evangelistic activities, Christmas, sports, New Years, impressions of events Dec. 1, 1942-Jan. 26, 1943, summary. (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Block #53-(continued) family studies, clique studies, personality studies. (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Block #54- statistics, personality profile, summary (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Block # 59- statistics, personality profile (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Block #60- statistics, interview, personality profile, summary (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Block #209- statistics and block meeting notes. (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Block #213- notes, Blocks #'ed 214, 215, 216, 219, 220, 221, 222, 227- charts (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Block #304- statistics, notes, manpower. (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Block #305- statistics, notes on manpower, history and census, block profile (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Block #307- notes on manpower, block profile (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Block # 308-notes (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Block #309- charts, statistics, interviews (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Block #310, #316- interview, charts (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Block #317- statistics, interview (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Block #318- interview, statistics, notes (manpower and housing survey), block study interview (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Block #322- statistics, block profile, interview, notes (manpower), block journal Oct. 14, 1942-Jan. 31, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Block #323- statistics, manpower study notes, interviews, summary (block profile), #342 chart (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Block #325- block profile (summary), statistics, interview, meeting minutes (family heads) Oct.-Dec. 1942, manpower study notes. (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Block #326- notes (housing and manpower), block summary, interview, notes (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Block #327- statistics, manpower notes (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Block #328- log, #329 charts, study, manpower notes, journal, interview, block profile, summary (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Block #330- manpower notes, study (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Statistics
    - Statistical summaries of Blocks #19, 30, 35, 46 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Unit I blocks statistical survey (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Unit III blocks statistical charts, graphs (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - "The Block as a social institution" study (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - "Block Leadership Breakdown" study notes (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Statistics not used in Block Study write-ups Unit I, II and III and grand total. (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - General reports, forms, population lists, general charts-- birth and death notes, male/female distribution, age grouping (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Census reports
    - Census Reports- Unit I (figures) census in age classification Dec. 1942-Nov. 1943, children's report Sept. 1942-Oct. 1943 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Census Reports- Unit II, census in age classification Nov. 1942-Oct. 1943, children's report Sept. 1942-Oct. 1943 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Census Reports- Unit III census in age classification Feb. 1943-Oct. 1943, children's report Sept. 1, 1942-Oct. 1943 (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Completed Block Census Report Forms, Blocks #3,4,19, 39, 42, 45, 46, 53, 54, 59, 60 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Census Intakes, registration, arrival, reports, #'s, lists Aug. 1942-July 1943 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Census Studies (figures and charts, notes for charts), temperature (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Census studies- religion (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Community enterprises
    - Establishment: events, conference minutes, history, appointment of trustees, board of trustees meetings Jan. 1943, disclosure of accounts (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Establishment: administration, WRA policy, letters, conversations (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Establishment: summary analysis, report on community enterprises and industry (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Cooperatives: reports on cooperative community enterprises and industry (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Cooperatives: administrative charts, information, petitions, memos, notices, press releases (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Cooperatives: meetings minutes and reports of cooperative education June-Aug. 1942, notes on 4-7 cooperative lectures, cooperative congress meetings (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Cooperatives: observational notes by BSR, chronological order of events (re. Coops) June 1942, remarks, opinions (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Cooperative congress: organization, report of cooperative includes: history, personnel, organizational chart, dominant sentiments (internal), sentiments of community, summary (role of COOP in Poston) (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Community Service Bureau- Block management proposed outline plan of the Community Service Bureau, consumers service bureau Mar. 8, 1943, Lapidary Bureau, Minerals Bureau May 16, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Official daily press bulletins, 1942 - Cooperative Congress Series #7: Associations (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Associations
    - Community activities: asministration-departmental circulars, charts, history of associations, analysis, programs (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Recreation: administration- general history, list of supervisors, reports (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Recreation meetings about sports (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Recreation meetings about Misc. and profiles of Golden Bears (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Recreation meetings about woman's organizations (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Recreation meetings about woman's organizations (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Recreation meetings about fujin kai (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Recreation meetings about girls activities (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Recreation meetings about girls activities (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Recreation meetings about YWCA (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Recreation meetings about Red Cross (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Recreation meetings about Junior Red Cross (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Recreation meetings about miscellaneous activities and also includes a report on adult education (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Entertainment reports, observations, minutes (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Health
    - General information including: notes about Dr. Pressman, organization chart, memos Sept. 18-Dec. 30, 1942, minutes of doctors' staff meetings May-Sept. 1942, observations and notes, lecture. (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Health statistics: births and deaths Aug. 1942-May 1943, summary of communicable and infectious diseases Agu. 1942-May 1943 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Hospital notes, orders, administration, cases, pharmacy notes, clinic notes (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Health cases, notes, mental patients, case notes (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Hospital personnel notes, general correspondence about health, minutes and notes from meetings (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Public Health notes, observations, examinations, facilities, sanitation department notes, staff meeting minutes, infant care (by block) (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Schools and Health memos (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Health/dust storm- study on actions, reactions to storm, observations, notes, damage survey (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Education
    - Schools- general information including: attitude study of Poston school kids, notes on Dr. Miles Cory (educational coordinator) principal's meeting notes (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Schools- statistics, schedules (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Schools- Program notes, notes on problems with the system, general notes (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Schools- construction (school building project), physical school environment (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Teachers- biographies and background information (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Teachers- administrative circulars Nov. 1942-June 1943 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Teachers- staff meeting minutes Sept. 14-Oct. 3, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Schools- proposed curriculum proceedings for Japanese Relocation Centers, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Schools- elementary- organization, objectives and progress reports, charts, program-course notes, goals, procedures (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Schools- High School- statistics, charts, notes (policies, organization, activities), elections, prom, curriculum bulletin, graduation plans and notes, "Mojave Memo" 1943 literary magazine, Poston slang report (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Schools- Senior class organization notes, notes, constitution (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Schools- teachers' progress reports grades 1-8, course evaluations 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Schools- Student Evaluation of Core 5-6 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Schools- Teachers' Progress (summary) reports 1942-1943, for high school courses (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Schools- High School Core Classes, teachers' progress (summary) reports 1942-1943 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Schools- High School Core Courses- student work (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Schools- Course outlines, Unit I, Jr. and Sr. High classes (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Schools- Course/Program outlines, Unit II (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Schools- Course/Program outlines, Unit III, meeting on policies (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Report- "Guidance and Evaluation in the Poston Schools" 1942-1943, by Frances Cushman, director of guidance (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Report- "Education Report" by Robert Saki (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Report- "Invitation is Freedom" Sept. 1942 - a proposal for a program of liberal adult education by Raymond Wilson (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Student Body Council- constitution, meeting minutes, election notes, assembly notes (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - National Student Relocation Council- correspondence, Poston Unit meeting notes, notes on program (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - PTA- meeting minutes, notes (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Library- report, history, observations, Poston Library News Mar. - June 1943 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Subsistence
    - Food- Reports: survey report July 20-Aug. 18, 1942, report on food Feb. 11, 1943, minutes of meeting Aug. 18, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Food- Block Survey on Food: #1-field notes blocks #2-28 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Food- Block Survey on Food: #1-field notes blocks #30-60 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Food- Food Survey #2- Oct.1942, reports, charts, memos (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Food- Food Survey #2- interviews, observations (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous field notes (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Food- administrative information-reports, meetings, memo (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Food-steward files, supply records, distributions (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Food- observations, interviews (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Housing-reports: on housing problem (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Housing- administration, information-memos, meetings, observations (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Housing- surveys on physical alteration of blocks, exterior improvements, charts (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Housing-surveys tally sheets (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Housing-applications for housing changes, Poston I, II, III Aug.- Sept. (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Housing-Block meeting Housing surveys Oct.-Feb. (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Housing- meetings and summary (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Transportation and supply- observations and sentiments (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Clothing- observations and sentiments on clothing allowance (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Maintenance- observations (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Work projects
    - General work projects- notes, interviews, reports (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Adobe- reports and observations (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Agriculture- report on fire break gang (diary of a work-crew) (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Agriculture- general administration- memos, letters, guayole project (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Agriculture- interviews, and observations of farmers (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Agriculture- administrative reports, meetings (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Agriculture- weekly reports Unit III Nov. 9, 1942-May 1, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Agriculture- division reports Unit II memos and daily diaries, June 1942-May 1943 truck crops (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Agriculture- division reports transports, equipment and maintenance (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Agriculture- division reports poultry (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - Agriculture- division reports apiary (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Agriculture- division reports irrigation and soil survey (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Agriculture- division reports landscaping and nursery (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - Agriculture- division reports hogs and swine (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Agriculture- division reports fish culture (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - Agriculture- division reports entomology (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - Agriculture- division reports labor (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Agriculture- division reports seed (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Agriculture- division reports marketing planners (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Camouflage- general administration memos and contracts (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - Camouflage- general administration memos and contracts (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - Camouflage- minutes of meetings and reports (chronology of project) (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - Camouflage- interviews and observations (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Cotton picking- report (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Industries- minutes (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Industries- observations (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Public Works- observations and records (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Employment
    - Employment- general forms, statistics, notes on laws and organization (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Employment- general notes (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Strike- chronologies of events, WRA reports on the "Poston Incident", 2 general reports on strike (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Strike- general reports on causes, notes on reactions, and actions taken after the incident (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Strike- AHL's notes and observations and interviews Nov. 1942-Feb. 1943 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Strike- per fujii and Uchida- petitions, correspondence, interviews (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Strike- AHL's Sociological Journal- notes on strike, Nov. 12-Dec. 21, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Strike- E.H. Spicer's "Running Account of General Strike" (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Strike- Emergency Committee meetings- minutes Nov. 21-24, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Strike- meetings about the Strike- temporary community council, committee of 72, staff meetings, teacher's meetings (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Strike- Central executive (and city planning board)- meetings minutes (formed after and as a result of strike) (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Strike- newspaper clippings (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Manpower- statistics, statistics from unemployment study, Merit rating board (notes) (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Manpower- Manpower Commission Meeting minutes Mar.-May 1943 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Manpower- Manpower Conference Mar. 12-13, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Leave- sentiments, notes, applications, memos (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Social welfare
    - Social Welfare Department- organization, outline, reports, notes on program (Box 10, Folder 17)